Walt Kuhn Family Papers and Armory Show
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Walt Kuhn Family papers and Armory Show records
1859-1978, bulk 1900-1949
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Kuhn, Walt
30.1 linear feet
The Walt Kuhn Family papers and Armory Show records measure 30.1 linear feet and date from 1859 to 1978, with the bulk of material dating from 1900 to 1949. Papers contain records of the legendary Armory Show of 1913, also known as the International Exhibition of Modern Art, which introduced modern European painting and sculpture to the American public. Papers also contain records of the Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS), the artist-run organization that mounted the Armory Show; records of the New York artists' clubs the Kit Kat Club (founded 1881) and the Penguin Club (founded 1917); and the personal and family papers of New York artist Walt Kuhn (1877-1949), one of the primary organizers of the Armory Show.
Provenance
The Walt Kuhn Family papers and Armory Show records were loaned for microfilming and later donated to the Archives of American Art by Walt Kuhn's daughter Brenda Kuhn in several installments between 1962 and 1979. An additional accession of letters, photographs, and an artifact was purchased by the Archives in 2000.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds the papers of Walter Pach, the European representative of the Armory Show.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of this collection was digitized in 2006 and 2009 and is available online via the Archives of American Art's website.
Materials that generally have not been scanned include medical records and records of routine financial transactions, duplicate originals and copies, negatives, slides, and large groups of news clippings. For many publications, such as books, catalogs, and pamphlets, only the cover and title pages have been scanned; complete publications are available by appointment.
Biographical Note
Walt Kuhn was an artist, teacher, advisor to art collectors, organizer, and promoter of modern art. He played a key role in the art scene of New York City in the early 20th century, and was among the small group that organized the infamous Armory Show of 1913, officially known as the International Exhibition of Modern Art, held at the 69th Regiment Armory building in New York City. After the Armory Show, Kuhn went on to a distinguished career as a painter. He was best known for his sober oil portraits of show people, clowns, acrobats, and circus performers, but was equally prolific in landscapes, still lifes, and figure and genre drawings.
Walt Kuhn was born in Brooklyn, NY in 1877. After a brief career as a bicycle shop owner in downtown Brooklyn, Kuhn traveled West in 1899 to San Francisco, CA and earned his living as a cartoonist for newspapers such as Wasp. After two years in California, he moved back East and then on to Europe to pursue further art training. He briefly attended the Académie Colarossi studio in Paris, but quickly moved to Munich where he joined the class of Heinrich von Zügel in the Royal Academy.
Kuhn returned to New York City in 1904 and took up an active role in the art scene there, participating in the Salmagundi Club and the Kit Kat Club, teaching at the New York School of Art, and cartooning for Life, Judge, Puck, and other publications. In 1910, he participated in an exhibition of Independent Artists on 35th St. with Robert Henri and met artist Arthur B. Davies.
In 1911, when the National Academy of Design opened their annual exhibition, Kuhn, Henry Fitch Taylor, Elmer MacRae, and Jerome Myers were exhibiting at Clara Potter Davidge's Madison Gallery. To these four young artists, the Academy exhibition was typically lackluster, and the attention it received was unwarranted. Sensing that they were not alone in their attitude, they decided to organize. They invited a dozen other artists to join them, thus forming the Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS). The group elected Kuhn Secretary and Arthur B. Davies President, and with the help of attorney and art collector John Quinn, they incorporated and began raising funds for an independent exhibition the following year.
In September of 1912, at Davies' suggestion, Kuhn traveled to Cologne, Germany to view the Sonderbund Internationale Kunst-Austellung. There he saw presented, in overwhelming volume, the work of his European contemporaries and their modern antecedents, the post-impressionists. He immediately began selecting and securing artwork for the upcoming AAPS exhibition. Kuhn traveled through Germany, Holland, France, and England, visiting private collectors, dealers, and artists. In Paris, Kuhn was joined by Davies and American artist and art agent Walter Pach. Kuhn and Davies sailed for New York in November, leaving the details of European arrangements to Pach.
The resulting Armory Show exhibition opened in New York in February 1913, and a selection of the foreign works traveled to Chicago and Boston in March and April. It included approximately 1300 American and European works of art, arranged in the exhibition space to advance the notion that the roots of modernism could be seen in the works of the old masters, from which the dramatically new art of living artists had evolved. Savvy and sensational publicity, combined with strategic word-of-mouth, resulted in attendance figures over 200,000 and over $44 thousand in sales. The Armory Show had demonstrated that modern art had a place in the public taste, that there was a market for it and legitimate critical support as well.
During the first World War, Kuhn stayed in NY and was active in the Kit Kat Club, an artists' club founded in 1881, which provided its members with collective studio space, live models, exhibitions, and an annual costume ball. In 1917, Kuhn founded another group called the Penguin Club, which had similar objectives to the Kit Kat Club, but with Kuhn himself as the gatekeeper. In addition to exhibitions and costume balls, the Penguin Club held summer outings and stag dinners, and maintained collective studio and exhibition space on East 15th Street in Manhattan. Its members included Americans and European artists displaced by the war in Europe. In the 1920s, Kuhn expanded a few sketches he had written for Penguin Balls into full-blown vaudeville productions, some of which were incorporated into larger musical revues such as The Merry Go Round and The 49ers and traveled around the country. Kuhn's theater work continued until 1928, and his fascination with show business continued to influence him throughout his life.
In the 1920s and 1930s, Kuhn gradually achieved recognition for his artwork, with sales to private collectors and dealers including Edith Halpert, Merritt Cutler, Lillie Bliss, John Quinn, and Marie Harriman. Kuhn also promoted other young painters whose work he liked, including Otis Oldfield, Lily Emmet Cushing, John Laurent, Frank di Gioia, and the self-taught Vermont artist Patsy Santo. Sometimes artists would contact him by mail, asking for lessons or advice. His lengthy letters to students offer coaching in technique and subject matter, as well as in the overall problem of success in art.
In 1929, Kuhn moved into the 18th St. studio that he would keep until the end of his life. He kept a rack of costumes in the studio, mostly made by Vera Kuhn, and his models, many of them stage and circus performers, would come and sit for Kuhn's portraits. The same year his painting The White Clown was exhibited at the newly established Museum of Modern Art in New York, bringing intense publicity and sales interest. Around this time, Kuhn began to receive the support of collector Duncan Phillips and curator Juliana Force of the Whitney Museum of American Art, both of whom made purchases and consistently exhibited his work.
Marie Norton Whitney Harriman, second wife of railroad magnate and diplomat W. Averell Harriman, shared a professional liaison with Kuhn that would take many forms and last until his death. Soon after the success of The White Clown, Kuhn established a relationship with the Marie Harriman Gallery, where he participated in group and solo shows during the height of his career. Kuhn also traveled with the Harrimans to Europe in 1931, where the three visited important private collections and acquired many valuable modern paintings for the Harrimans. Their collection, so heavily influenced by Kuhn's ideas about art, would eventually go to the National Gallery of Art.
Kuhn was an artist who understood the art business and never shied away from it. For Kuhn, promoting the ideas and practitioners of a certain brand of modernism was an expression of both aesthetic ideology and pragmatic self-interest. His contribution to the public discourse on modernism situated his own work at the heart of art history and the marketplace. Regardless of his motivations, he was indisputably a key player at a pivotal time in American art, when academic art was riotoulsy overturned to make way for modernism. His paintings are now held in major museum collections around the country, where most of them arrived with bequests from the collectors Kuhn had cultivated so carefully in his lifetime.
Sources consulted for this biography include The Story of the Armory Show (1988) by Milton W. Brown, Walt Kuhn, Painter: His Life and Work (1978) by Philip Rhys Adams, and "Walt Kuhn" by Frank Getlein, in the 1967 catalog of the Kennedy Galleries, Inc.
Scope and Content Note
The Walt Kuhn Family papers and Armory Show records measure 30.1 linear feet and date from 1859 to 1978, with the bulk of material dating from 1900 to 1949. Papers contain records of the legendary Armory Show of 1913, also known as the International Exhibition of Modern Art, which introduced modern European painting and sculpture to the American public. Papers also contain records of the Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS), the artist-run organization that mounted the Armory Show; records of the New York artists' clubs the Kit Kat Club (founded 1881) and the Penguin Club (founded by Kuhn, 1917); and the personal and family papers of New York artist Walt Kuhn (1877-1949), one of the primary organizers of the Armory Show.
As Secretary for the AAPS, Kuhn retained the bulk of existing records of that organization and of the Armory Show. Minutes and correspondence make up most of the AAPS records (Series 2), as well as documents related to John Quinn's legal brief against a tariff on imported works of living artists. Armory Show Records (Series 1) include personal letters, voluminous business correspondence, a record book, miscellaneous notes, inventories and shipping records, two large scrapbooks, printed materials, a small number of photographs, and retrospective accounts of the show. The printed materials and photographs in Kit Kat Club and Penguin Club Records reflect Kuhn's deep involvement in those clubs.
The Walt Kuhn Family Papers (Series 4) contain records of his artwork, career, travels, personal and professional associations, family members, and work in vaudeville, film, and interior design. Notable among the family papers are illustrated letters and other cartoons; sketches, drawings, watercolors, and prints; candid letters from Walt to Vera Kuhn discussing art scene politics and personalities in New York, Paris, Chicago, Los Angeles, San Francisco, Florida, and the Midwest; general correspondence with artists, dealers, collectors, journalists, writers, models, and fans; notes in index card files containing biographical anecdotes of the Kuhns' many contacts; provenance files that document the origin and fate of Kuhn's paintings, sculptures, and prints; papers relating to Kuhn's exhibitions and his relationships with the Marie Harriman Gallery and Durand-Ruel Gallery; and photographs and drawings depicting Kuhn's early years in Munich, Germany and Fort Lee, NJ; trips to Nova Scotia, New England, the Western United States, and Europe; New York and summer studios, among other subjects.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Association of American Painters and Sculptors (New York, N.Y.); Penguin Club (New York, N.Y.); Kit Kat Club (New York, N.Y.); Armory Show (1913: New York, N.Y.); International Exhibition of Modern Art
Subjects-Topical:
New York school of art; Art schools -- Photographs; Watercolor painting, American; Artists' models -- Photographs; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Exhibitions; Art -- Societies, etc. -- New York (State) -- New York; Etchers; Lithographers; Watercolorists -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Travel diaries; Photographs; Works of art; Sketches
Names:
Oldfield, Otis, 1890-1969; Kuhn, Vera, d. 1961; Pach, Walter, 1883-1958; Quinn, John, 1870-1924; Rainford, Percy photographer; Sheeler, Charles, 1883-1965; Davies, Arthur B. (Arthur Bowen), 1862-1928; Kuhn, Brenda, 1911-; Weston, Edward, 1886-1958 photographer
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into 4 series, with multiple subseries in Series 1 and 4.
Series 1: Armory Show Records, 1912-1963 (Boxes 1-2, 27-31, OV 36; 3.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS) Records, 1911-1914, undated (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Kit Kat Club and Penguin Club Records, 1909-1923, undated (Box 3, 32, OV 37-38; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Walt Kuhn Family Papers, 1859-1978, undated (Box 3-26, 32-35, OV 39-55; 25.8 linear feet)
In general, documents are arranged chronologically, alphabetically, or by type of material. Copy negatives and copy prints made from documents in this collection have been filed separately from originals, in a folder marked "copy." Duplicates of original records made or obtained by the Kuhns have been filed separately as well.
Existing envelopes are filed in front of correspondence and enclosures directly after. Correspondence in the Armory Show Records and AAPS Records is arranged alphabetically, and correspondents are listed in the box inventory following series descriptions below.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Armory Show Records, 1912-1963, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-2, 27-31, OV 36; 3.6 linear feet)
  As Secretary of the Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS), and as selector of European works included in the show, Walt Kuhn was heavily involved in the conception, organization, and production of the International Exhibition of Modern Art, more commonly known as the Armory Show of 1913. Records in this series document the exhibition, including the selection of art work in Europe and the U.S., selection of venues, negotiation of contracts, production of the exhibitions, publicity, promotion, sales, and the wide array of responses to the exhibitions in New York, Chicago, and Boston.
  Types of material found in this series include correspondence, clippings, notes, inventories, insurance policies, mailing lists, a record book, writings, entry cards, marked and unmarked catalogs, pamphlets, postcards, floor plans, photographs, scrapbooks and memorabilia related to the exhibition. Also included are a handful of records related to retrospective accounts and exhibitions produced in 1938 and 1963 for the 25th and 50th anniversaries of the exhibition, including Walt Kuhn's 1938 pamphlet, "The Story of the Armory Show."
  Records relating to the formation and administration of the AAPS are found in Series 2.
  This series is arranged according the following 9 subseries:
  1.1: Correspondence, 1912-1914
  1.2: Domestic Art Committee Records, 1913
  1.3: European Entry Cards, circa 1912
  1.4: Notes, 1912-1913
  1.5: Printed Material and Memorabilia, 1912-1913
  1.6: Writings of Walt Kuhn, 1912-1913
  1.7: Photographs, 1912-1913
  1.8: Scrapbooks, 1912-1913
  1.9: Retrospective Materials, 1938-1963, undated
  This series has been scanned in entirety with the exception of duplicates and copies.
  - Correspondence, 1912-1914, 1.1:
    This series contains correspondence among Armory Show organizers, artists, dealers, collectors, vendors, publicists, and the public concerning the planning, production, and reception of the exhibition in New York, Chicago, and Boston.
    Unless otherwise noted, incoming and outgoing correspondence has been interfiled and arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Often only unsigned carbons of outgoing correspondence exists for a listed correspondent. When a correspondent has less than five items in a series, their letters have been placed in general alphabetical files, whose contents are listed under their file heading. Announcements written by AAPS members and sent to multiple recipients have been filed under the heading "Association of American Painters and Sculptors," regardless of the signature.
    Correspondence is divided into the following six groups.
    1.1.1: Organizers' Letters
    1.1.2: Artists and Lenders Correspondence
    1.1.3: Insurers, Packers, and Shippers Correspondence
    1.1.4: Publicity
    1.1.5: Traveling Exhibition
    1.1.6: Sales Correspondence
    Details of the content and arrangement of each group can be found with their box and folder listing below.
    - Organizers' Letters, 1912-1913, 1.1.1:
      Organizers' Letters include letters written by Arthur B. Davies and Walt Kuhn. Recipients include Walter Pach, Walt Kuhn, and Vera Kuhn. Letters describe Kuhn's and Davies' travel to Europe to collect works to exhibit, preparations in New York, and the traveling exhibitions in Chicago and Boston. Several letters from Walt Kuhn are illustrated, and a floor plan of a proposed installation in the Armory is among Davies' letters. One postcard to Vera Kuhn from Boston is signed by Maurice and Charles Prendergast and Frederick James Gregg, as well as by Walt Kuhn.
      Additional letters from Walt Kuhn to his wife before and after his Armory Show activities can be found in Series 4.2: Walt Kuhn Letters to Family.
      Letters are separated by author and arranged chronologically.
      - Arthur B. Davies, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Arthur B. Davies (copies), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Walt Kuhn to Vera Kuhn, 1912-1913, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
      - Walt Kuhn to Vera Kuhn (copies), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Walt Kuhn to Walter Pach, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Walt Kuhn to Walter Pach (copies), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Artists and Lenders Correspondence, 1912-1913, 1.1.2:
      Artists and Lenders Correspondence includes correspondence between organizers and artists, dealers, collectors, and other potential contributors to the exhibition. Included are letters from Oscar Bluemner, Constantin Brancusi, Robert Delaunay, Raymond Duchamp-Villon, Arthur J. Eddy, Erich Heckel, Edvard Munch, Maurice Prendergast, John Quinn, Odilon Redon, Charles Sheeler, Alfred Stieglitz, Leo and Michael Stein, Ambrose Vollard, and Jack B. Yeats, among others.
      This group is divided geographically between domestic and European correspondents, and is arranged alphabetically by name. Americans living in Europe at the time of the show are generally filed in the European correspondence. In addition to letters, this series contains occasional translations of letters from French or German, and a handful of lists of works or notes found with correspondence.
      Additional correspondence with artists, dealers, and patrons can be found in Armory Show Sales Correspondence (Series 1.1.6).
      - Domestic, A-D, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Alger, John H.
        Andrews, J.B.
        Association of American Painters and Sculptors
        Barnard, George Gray
        Beach, Chester
        Birnbaum, Martin
        Bjorkman, Olaf
        Bliss, Lily
        Bloodgood, M. Seymour
        Bluemner, Oscar
        Bush, Mrs. Wendell T.
        Brewer, Bessie M.
        Brown, F. William
        Chaffee, O.N.
        Cheever, Elizabeth S.
        Chew, Amos
        Coates, Miss
        Currier, Miss (Daughter of J. Frank Currier)
        Dabo, Mrs. Leon
        Dabo, Leon
        Dasburg, Andrew (see Johnson, Grace M.)
        Davidson, Jo
        Dodge, Mrs. Edwin Shurill (Mabel)
        Drake, Alexander W.
        Dreier, Katherine S.
        Dreyfous, Florence
      - Domestic, E-J, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Eddy, Arthur J.
        Eels, Jean
        Fairbanks, Mr. (Boston)
        Field, Hamilton
        Flint, Annie Austin
        Freeman, Charles H.
        Gans, Mrs. Howard
        Gellatly, John
        Glintenkamp, Henry I.
        The Gorham Co.
        Guinness, Mrs. Arthur
        Guinness, Mrs. Benjamin S.
        Hannah, Zoe
        Hardon, Mrs. Henry W.
        Harley, Charles R.
        Hartshorn, Robert
        Haviland, Paul
        Horter, E.
        Johnson, Grace M.
      - Domestic, E-J (copies), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Domestic, Keller, Henry G., 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Domestic, K-R, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Kuhn, Walt
        Loewenstein, Dr. Helen C.
        Macbeth, William
        Mather, Frank J. Jr.
        McGrath, Mrs. F.S.
        McKinney, Miss E.
        Meltzer, Charlotte
        Morgan, Daniel H.
        Ninkivell, Frank S.
        Norton, Mrs. Porter
        Oakman, John
        Of, George F.
        Pepper, Charles Hovey
        Pleuthner, Walter Karl
        Potter, Louis (see Gorham Co.)
        Prendergast, Maurice
        Pruyn, Francis L.
        Quinn, John
        Reisinger, Hugo
        Rumsey, Mrs. Charles Cary
      - Domestic, Stieglitz, Alfred, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Domestic, Stieglitz, Alfred (copies), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Domestic, S-Y, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Schamberg, Morton L.
        Sears, Mrs. Montgomery
        Sheeler, Charles R.
        Spingarn, A.B.
        Stein, Mrs. (New York)
        Sumner, John Osborne
        Tison, Mrs. Alexander
        Torrey, Frederic C.
        Walter, Martha
        Willard, Mary Livingston
        Williams, Lloyd
        Young, Arthur
      - Europe, Artz and de Bois, (see also Bois, J.H. de) 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Europe, Bernheim Jeune and Cie., 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Europe, Butler, Theodore E., 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Europe, Druet, Emile (Galerie E. Druet) 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Europe, General A-D and illegible, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        [illegible signature]
        Archipenko, Alexander
        Bernard, Joseph
        Bois, J.H. de
        Bourgeois, Stephan
        Brancusi, Constantin
        Chabaud, Auguste
        Chadbourne, Mrs. Emily Crane (see Molitor, M. et Mme.)
        Delaunay, Robert
        Dell, Robert (The Burlington Magazine, The Nation)
        Dirks, Rudolph
        Duchamp-Villon, Raymond
        Dunoyer de Segonzac, André
        Durand-Ruel and Sons (Paris)
      - Europe, General A-D and illegible (copies), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Europe, M. Flechtheim (Alfred Flechtheim), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Europe, Hans Goltz (Neue Kunst), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Europe, General, H-N, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Heckel, Erich
        Howard, Cecil
        Kirstein, Alfred
        John, Augustus
        Kahnweiler, Henry
        Lehmbruck, Wilhelm
        Molitor, M. et Mme.
        Munch, Edvard
        Nadelman, Eli
        Neue Seccession Berlin
      - Europe, General, H-N (copies), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Europe, Thannhauser, Heinrich (Moderne Galerie), 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Europe, General, P-Y, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Pryde, James
        Redon, Odilon
        Reimers, Hermann
        Roosevelt, A.
        Rosenberg, Leonce
        Segal, Arthur
        Sickert, Walter
        Stein, Leo